<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xml:id="project_description_0001.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Editorial Declaration</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </author>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2022">2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
                     for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2022-02-24">text created</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Editorial Declaration</head>
            <p></p>
            <div>
               <head>Presentation of the Material</head>
                  <p>By default, the edited documents are presented in accordance with the conventions followed in <hi rend="italics">The Complete Works of W. H. Auden</hi> (1993-2022), edited by Edward Mendelson. Optionally, original text features, such as deletions, can be displayed, and users can modify presentation preferences.</p>                   
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           The default view offers the following features:
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>one view per page recto and verso</item>
                              <item>vertical arrangements of texts that partially represent the original layout</item>
                              <item>different fonts to represent handwriting (Times New Roman), typewriting (Courier New), and print (Arial)</item>
                              <item>reading versions of texts that do not contain deletions, underlines, additional typographic whitespace, or indications of unclear characters</item>
                              <item>italics to represent originally underlined text</item>
                              <item>indications of undecipherable characters (if not deleted)</item>
                              <item>facsimiles displayed through a plugin viewer, with controls to adjust image size</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           The following display options are available:
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>original text features: deletions, underlines, additional typographic whitespace</item>
                              <item>indications of unclear characters, which cannot be transcribed with certainty</item>
                              <item>choice of fonts and font sizes</item>
                              <item>full-screen view</item>
                              <item>text-focus view without facsimile</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Facsimile Documentation</head>
                  <p>The documents have been reproduced at 600 dpi and 24 bit/RGB by means of an Image Access WideTEK®25 color flatbed scanner and saved in an uncompressed TIFF format. Selected materials (Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin with Typescript W. H. Auden "Joseph Weinheber" 1965-04-28 and with Typescript W. H. Auden Translation "Joseph Weinheber"; Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1969-06-10) have been digitized at 603.1 dpi and 24 bit by means of a Phase One XF IQ3 100MP medium-format camera with a Schneider Kreuznach 80mm f/2.8 leaf shutter lens. In order to accelerate upload, the digital reproductions of documents are displayed at a lower resolution on the website.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
               <head>Transcription Guidelines</head>
                  <p>Source transcriptions as encoded in TEI/XML represent the spelling, punctuation, and revisions as they appear, aiming for minimal editorial intervention or interpretation.</p>                   
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="1">
                           Spelling
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="1.1">The original spelling in both manuscripts and typescripts is retained, even if irregular.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin with Typescript W. H. Auden "Freedom and Necessity in the Arts" 1970-05-21, page 9, line 8) -->
                              <item n="1.2">Characters that cannot be transcribed with certainty are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be highlighted in grey on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1973-09-24, page 3, line 9) -->
                              <item n="1.3">Handwritten characters are not marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML when they can be identified as a consistent and typical feature of the respective author's handwriting.</item><!-- (example: "address", Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-15, page 3, line 25) -->
                              <item n="1.4">Signatures are not marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]>.</item>
                              <item n="1.5">Characters that cannot be transcribed are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>gap<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and represented by means of square brackets on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 7) -->
                              <item n="1.6">Superscripts have not yet been marked up and are not represented on the web page.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="2">Numericals
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="2.1">For typescripts, the characters 'I' (uppercase i) and 'O' (uppercase o) designating the numbers 1 and 0 (zero), respectively, are preserved.</item>
                              <item n="2.2">For manuscripts, the anglophone variant writing of the numeral 1 is represented by '1'.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item> 
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="3">Punctuation and Spaces
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="3.1">The original punctuation is retained, even if irregular.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 4) -->
                              <item n="3.2">Punctuation signs that cannot be transcribed with certainty are rendered by UTF-8/Unicode symbols that represent a graphical approximation, marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1965-09-29, page 3, line 16) -->
                              <item n="3.3">For manuscripts, when spaces before or after punctuation marks are significantly smaller than the spaces separating words in the surrounding text, no spaces are transcribed.</item><!-- (example: Letter W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1962-09-11, page 3, line 12)-->
                              <item n="3.4">For manuscripts, the length of spaces between words is regularized and represented as either single space or no space.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 6) -->
                              <item n="3.5">For typescripts, the exact number of spaces within sentences is preserved and marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]> in XML.</item><!-- (example: Typescript Stella Musulin "In Retrospect" [?], page 1, line 2) -->
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="4">Original line breaks and divisions between blocks of text are retained.</item>                           
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="5">Underline
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="5.1">Underlines are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>hi rend="underline"<![CDATA[>]]> and can be graphically represented on the web page.</item>
                              <item n="5.2">Underlines are not represented if they form part of signatures.</item>
                              <item n="5.3">Underlines in typescripts are rendered precisely and include, for instance, empty spaces before or after words if they are underlined in the source document; transcriptions of underlines in manuscripts ignore underlined spaces before or after words.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="6">Characters whose legibility is impaired by smudges and overwritings are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be represented in grey on the web page.</item>
                     </list>   
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="7">Revisions
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="7.1">Deletions of text are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be represented on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1964-12-23, page 3, line 26) -->
                              <item n="7.2">For overwritings in manuscripts and typescripts, we have accepted the orthographically or grammatically accurate versions as corrections, even if the actual sequences of textual layers cannot be reconstructed.</item><!--  (example: Typescript Stella Musulin "In Retrospect" [?], page 1, line 27) -->
                              <item n="7.3">For transcriptions of typescripts, we accept the use of the signs 'x', 'm', 'z', and '-' as indicating deletions where such deletion seems plausible.</item>
                              <item n="7.4">When additions are inserted into manuscripts or typescripts, surrounding spaces are included in ways that are coherent with the general use of spaces in the respective texts.</item><!-- examples!  (that especially concerns spaces after punctuation in typescripts) -->
                              <item n="7.5">When additions replace deleted words in typescripts, they are inserted directly after the deletions without additional spaces in between.</item>
                              <item n="7.6">When it is uncertain whether characters have been deleted, the passage in question is marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>gap reason="deleted"/<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>del/<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>unclear/<![CDATA[>]]>.</item>
                              <item n="7.7">For typescripts by Musulin, we accept handwritten underlines of deleted passages as cancelled deletions.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                             
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="8">Pre-printed Components and Postal Additions
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="8.1">Pre-printed letter heads and sender addresses are transcribed.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-06, page 2, lines 1-3) -->
                              <item n="8.2">Image captions in postcards are transcribed.</item><!--  (example: Autograph Note Signed Michael O'Sullivan to Stella Musulin [?], page 1, lines 1-2, 12-15) -->
                              <item n="8.3">Postmarks and stamps are not transcribed.</item>
                              <item n="8.4">Pre-printed postal texts and images in telegrams and aerograms are not rendered in the transcriptions.</item><!--  (example: Telegram W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1971-05-13) -->
                           </list>
                        </item>                           
                     </list>    
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>