<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xml:id="project_description_0001.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Documentation</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
               <name>Grigoriou, Dimitra</name>
            </author>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2022">2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
                     for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2022-02-24">text created</change>
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2023-07-26">update image digitization section</change>
         <change who="dgrigoriou smayer tfruehwirth" when="2023-10-17">update regarding correspondence schema</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Documentation</head>
            <p></p>
            <div>
               <head>Presentation of the Material</head>
                  <p>By default, the edited documents are presented in accordance with the conventions followed in <hi rend="italics">The Complete Works of W. H. Auden</hi> (1993-2022), edited by Edward Mendelson. Optionally, original text features, such as deletions, can be displayed, and users can modify presentation preferences.</p>                   
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           The default view offers the following features:
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>one view per page recto and verso (with the exception of photographs glued onto pages of photo albums)</item>
                              <item>vertical arrangements of texts that partially represent the original layout</item>
                              <item>different fonts to represent handwriting (Times New Roman), typewriting (Courier New), and print (Arial)</item>
                              <item>reading versions of texts that do not contain deletions, underlines, additional typographic whitespace, or indications of unclear characters</item>
                              <item>italics to represent originally underlined text</item>
                              <item>indications of undecipherable characters (if not deleted)</item>
                              <item>facsimiles displayed through a plugin viewer, with controls to adjust image size</item>
                              <!-- detailed view of metadata -->
                              <!-- correspondence metadata --> 
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           The following display options are available:
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>original text features: deletions, underlines, additional typographic whitespace</item>
                              <item>indications of unclear characters, which cannot be transcribed with certainty</item>
                              <item>labeling of entities (persons, places, institutions, works, events)</item><!-- activating the comment section -->
                              <item>choice of fonts and font sizes</item>
                              <item>full-screen view</item>
                              <item>text-focus view without facsimile</item>
                              <!-- addition of editorial comments/level of uncertainy/responsibility -->
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Image Digitization</head>
                  <p>The documents have been reproduced at 600 dpi and 24 bit/RGB through an Image Access WideTEK®25 color flatbed scanner and saved in an uncompressed TIFF format. Selected materials (images 5 and 6 in https://amp.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp-transcript__0039.html, images 3 and 4 in https://amp.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp-transcript__0040.html) have been digitized at 603.1 dpi and 24 bit by means of a Phase One XF IQ3 100MP medium-format camera with a Schneider Kreuznach 80mm f/2.8 leaf shutter lens. The high-resolution digital reproductions can be accessed via https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/auden-musulin-papers/facs. On the website, images are provided through IIIF.</p>
                  <p>The images of Autograph Letter Signed Stella Musulin to Christine Busta 1962-05-23 have been created by the Literary Archive of the Austrian National Library.</p>
                  <!-- maybe refer to the image rights? -->
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Disclaimer v0.3</head>
                  <p>The facsimile view is not yet optimized for the mobile version of the web application.</p>
               </div>   
               <div>
               <head>Transcription and Markup Guidelines of v0.3</head>
                  <p>Source transcriptions as encoded in TEI/XML represent the spelling, punctuation, and revisions as they appear, aiming for minimal editorial intervention or interpretation.</p>                   
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="1">
                           Spelling
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="1.1">The original spelling in both manuscripts and typescripts is retained, even if irregular.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin with Typescript W. H. Auden "Freedom and Necessity in the Arts" 1970-05-21, page 9, line 8) -->
                              <item n="1.2">Characters that cannot be transcribed with certainty are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be highlighted in grey on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1973-09-24, page 3, line 9) -->
                              <item n="1.3">Handwritten characters are not marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML when they can be identified as a consistent and typical feature of the respective author's handwriting.</item><!-- (example: "address", Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-15, page 3, line 25) -->
                              <item n="1.4">Signatures are not marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]>.</item>
                              <item n="1.5">Characters that cannot be transcribed are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>gap<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and represented by means of square brackets on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 7) -->
                              <item n="1.6">Superscripts in the original documents have not yet been marked up and are not represented on the web page.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="2">Numericals
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="2.1">For typescripts, the characters 'I' (uppercase i) and 'O' (uppercase o) designating the numbers 1 and 0 (zero), respectively, are preserved.</item>
                              <item n="2.2">For manuscripts, the anglophone variant writing of the numeral 1 is represented by '1'.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item> 
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="3">Punctuation and Spaces
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="3.1">The original punctuation is retained, even if irregular.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 4) -->
                              <item n="3.2">Punctuation signs that cannot be transcribed with certainty are rendered by UTF-8/Unicode symbols that represent a graphical approximation, marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1965-09-29, page 3, line 16) -->
                              <item n="3.3">For manuscripts, when spaces before or after punctuation marks are significantly smaller than the spaces separating words in the surrounding text, no spaces are transcribed.</item><!-- (example: Letter W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1962-09-11, page 3, line 12)-->
                              <item n="3.4">For manuscripts, the length of spaces between words is regularized and represented as either single space or no space.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 6) -->
                              <item n="3.5">For typescripts, the exact number of spaces before and within sentences is preserved and marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]> in TEI/XML. For spaces in two-column layout pages, most likely generated by means of the tab function or by resetting the typewriter's margin stop, approximative values of spaces have been indicated.</item>
                              <item n="3.6">Indentations of typed lines (of poetry) without reference value in relation to the left-hand margin are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>space extent="undefined quantity of characters"<![CDATA[>]]>.</item><!-- example: doc 0038 -->
                              <item n="3.7">Changes in the left-hand margins of typescripts are not marked up as indentations (by means of <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]>) if they appear to result from reinsertations of the sheets of paper or resets of margins on the typewriter that do not appear meaningful.</item><!-- doc 18, p 17; docs 27, 43, p 3 -->
                              <item n="3.8">Spaces that precede printed text are disregarded.</item><!-- (example: transcript_0001, page 2, line 3) -->
                              <item n="3.9">Blank lines between lines of writing are disregarded.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="4">Page Layout
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="4.1">Original line breaks are retained within structural elements of text, but not in between block-level elements (such as in between <![CDATA[<]]>p<![CDATA[>]]>, <![CDATA[<]]>salute<![CDATA[>]]>, or <![CDATA[<]]>signed<![CDATA[>]]> elements). Within structural elements, the TEI <![CDATA[<]]>lb<![CDATA[>]]> element represents standard line spacing (most likely produced by operating the typewriter's carriage-return lever); in between elements, spacing (possibly produced by means of operating the typewriter's variable line spacing knob) can vary, which is not represented in the markup.</item>
                              <item n="4.2">For non-correspondence documents as well as for telegrams and aerograms, a non-specific container structure is currently used: the transcription of each document is contained within a TEI <![CDATA[<]]>div<![CDATA[>]]> element; each transcription is subdivided by means of <![CDATA[<]]>pb<![CDATA[>]]>, <![CDATA[<]]>p<![CDATA[>]]>, and <![CDATA[<]]>lg<![CDATA[>]]> elements.</item>
                              <item n="4.3">For correspondence documents, excluding telegrams and aerograms, a specific and semantically more detailed TEI-conformant container structure is used. The most important structural elements are the following: <![CDATA[<]]>div type="transcription"<![CDATA[>]]> can contain <![CDATA[<]]>div type="envelope"<![CDATA[>]]> and <![CDATA[<]]>div type="letter"<![CDATA[>]]>; <![CDATA[<]]>div type="letter"<![CDATA[>]]> can include <![CDATA[<]]>div type="letter_message"<![CDATA[>]]> and <![CDATA[<]]>div type="poem"<![CDATA[>]]>; <![CDATA[<]]>div type="letter_message"<![CDATA[>]]> can contain <![CDATA[<]]>opener<![CDATA[>]]> and <![CDATA[<]]>closer<![CDATA[>]]> containers; <![CDATA[<]]>opener<![CDATA[>]]> groups together dateline and salutation information from the start of the correspondence item; <![CDATA[<]]>closer<![CDATA[>]]> groups together salutation and signature information from the end of the correspondence item; <![CDATA[<]]>div type="poem"<![CDATA[>]]> can be further structured through the <![CDATA[<]]>cb<![CDATA[>]]> milestone element and can contain <![CDATA[<]]>head<![CDATA[>]]> and <![CDATA[<]]>lg<![CDATA[>]]> elements; <![CDATA[<]]>lg<![CDATA[>]]> nodes include <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]> and <![CDATA[<]]>l<![CDATA[>]]> elements.</item>
                              <item n="4.4">The vertical succession of text elements is represented; their horizontal arrangement is disregarded.</item>
             <!-- update -->  <item n="4.5">Line numbers are added to the website display, with separate numbering systems for prose and verse, respectively.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>   
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="5">Underline
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="5.1">Underlines are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>hi rend="underline"<![CDATA[>]]> and can optionally be graphically represented on the web page. By default, they are represented in italics on the web page.</item>
                              <item n="5.2">Underlines are not represented if they form part of signatures.</item>
                              <item n="5.3">Underlines in typescripts are rendered precisely and include, for instance, empty spaces before or after words if they are underlined in the source document; transcriptions of underlines in manuscripts ignore underlined spaces before or after words.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                          
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="6">Characters whose legibility is impaired by smudges and overwritings are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be represented in grey on the web page.</item>
                     </list>   
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="7">Revisions
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="7.1">Deletions of text are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and can be represented on the web page.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1964-12-23, page 3, line 26) -->
                              <item n="7.2">For revisions in manuscripts and typescripts, we have accepted the orthographically or grammatically accurate versions as corrections, even if the actual sequences of textual layers cannot be reconstructed.</item><!--  (example: Typescript Stella Musulin "In Retrospect" [?], page 1, line 27) -->
                              <item n="7.3">For transcriptions of typescripts - in addition to handwritten deletions - we accept the use of the typed signs 'x', 'm', 'z', 'y', '-', and '/' as indicating deletions where such deletion seems plausible.</item>
                              <item n="7.4">Additions have not yet been marked up and are not represented on the website, but are treated as part of the original documents.</item>
                              <item n="7.5">When additions are inserted into manuscripts or typescripts, surrounding spaces are included in ways that are coherent with the general use of spaces in the respective texts.</item><!-- examples!  (that especially concerns spaces after punctuation in typescripts) -->
                              <item n="7.6">When additions replace deleted words in typescripts, they are inserted directly after the deletions without additional spaces in between.</item>
                              <item n="7.7">When it is uncertain whether characters have been deleted, the passage in question is marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>gap reason="deleted"/<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>del/<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>unclear/<![CDATA[>]]>.</item>
                              <item n="7.8">For typescripts by Musulin, we accept handwritten underlines of deleted passages as cancelled deletions.</item>
                              <item n="7.9">Multiple overwritings in the same place of a typescript (when character 'x' is overwritten by character 'y', which, in turn, is overwritten by 'z') are represented as nested deletions: '<![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]><![CDATA[<]]>del<![CDATA[>]]>x<![CDATA[</]]>del<![CDATA[>]]>y<![CDATA[</]]>del<![CDATA[>]]>z'</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                             
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="8">Pre-printed Components and Postal Additions
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="8.1">Pre-printed letter heads and sender addresses are transcribed.</item><!-- (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-06, page 2, lines 1-3) -->
                              <item n="8.2">Image captions in postcards are transcribed.</item><!--  (example: Autograph Note Signed Michael O'Sullivan to Stella Musulin [?], page 1, lines 1-2, 12-15) -->
                              <item n="8.3">Postmarks and stamps are not transcribed in the <![CDATA[<]]>text<![CDATA[>]]> part. Organization (e.g., post office), place, date, and time information has been extracted and included in the <![CDATA[<]]>correspDesc<![CDATA[>]]> section of the <![CDATA[<]]>teiHeader<![CDATA[>]]>. In accordance with the TEI P5 Guidelines, the individual stages in the correspondence process are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>correspAction<![CDATA[>]]>. The following values of the @type attribute are used: "sent" for information that refers to the first processing of the correspondence item by the outgoing post office as retrieved from the postmark; "transmitted" for information on the further processing of the correspondence item by the incoming post office(s) as retrieved from the backstamp(s); "redirected" for information on the place (as well as, if applicable, on the person or organization) related to redirecting the unopened correspondence item to another destination; "received" for information on the person (and, if applicable, place) related to the last indicated destination. Information on the place and date of writing is encoded within the <![CDATA[<]]>fileDesc<![CDATA[>]]> node of the <![CDATA[<]]>teiHeader<![CDATA[>]]>. Where no envelope has been preserved, only the <![CDATA[<]]>correspAction<![CDATA[>]]> of @type "received" is documented. Copies of correspondence items are not treated as correspondence items and no <![CDATA[<]]>correspDesc<![CDATA[>]]> has been recorded.</item>
                              <item n="8.4">Pre-printed postal texts and images in telegrams and aerograms are not rendered in the transcriptions.</item><!--  (example: Telegram W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1971-05-13) -->
                              <item n="8.5">Watermarks have not yet been transcribed.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>                           
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="9">Writing technologies
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="9.1">Writing technologies (handwriting, typewriting, print) are marked up by means of the <![CDATA[<]]>... hand="..."<![CDATA[>]]> attribute in XML and are represented through different fonts on the web page.</item>
                              <item n="9.2">The <![CDATA[<]]>handShift<![CDATA[>]]> element indicates an immediate change of writing technologies.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">       
                        <item n="10">Photographs  
                           <list rend="numbered">
                              <item n="10.1">All texts pertaining to the photograph documents are transcribed.</item>
                              <item n="10.2">Persons depicted in the photographs or referred to in the accompanying texts are recorded in the <![CDATA[<]]>particDesc<![CDATA[>]]> section of the <![CDATA[<]]>teiHeader<![CDATA[>]]>.</item>
                              <!-- image rights appear in metadata section -->
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list rend="numbered">
                        <item n="11">Extra-textual entities (persons, places, organizations, literary works, and events) are marked up in XML by means of <![CDATA[<]]>rs<![CDATA[>]]> and can optionally be displayed on the website, where they are enriched with additional information and norm-data identifiers.</item>
                     </list>
                  <!-- list rend="numbered">
                     <item n="12">Editiorial comments are marked up in XML by means of <![CDATA[<]]>ana<![CDATA[>]]> and can optionally be displayed on the website, where they are enriched with additional information acquired through research and norm-and machine-readable data identifiers.</item>
                  </list>-->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>